Guide to the Future Directions in Computing Education Summit White Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Future Directions in Computing Education Summit white papers
2013
SC1186
9.62 megabyte(s) (45 computer files)
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Scope and Contents
NSF funded a CS Education Research Summit with the goal of exploring future questions and directions in CS education research. The summit ran January 8-9, 2014 in Orlando, Florida, and was held immediately after the CE21 meeting.
Access Terms
Ashcraft, Catherine; Bienkowski, Marie; Boyer, Kristy; Brennan, Karen; Brown, Quincy; Caspersen, Michael; Century, Jeanne; Cooper, Steve; Danielak, Brian.; Dann, Wanda; Denner, Jill; DiSalvo, Betsy; Doane, William; Edwards, Stephen; Eisenberg, Michael; Fenwick, James; Fincher, Sally; Fisler, Kathi; Gardner-McCune, Christina; Goode, Joanna; Grover, Shuchi; Guzdial, Mark; Hodari, Apriel; Hundhausen, Christopher; Kafai, Yasmin; Kolikant, Yifat Ben-David; Kurtz, Barry L.; Kurtz, Barry; Ladner, Richard; Lee, Cynthia; Lewis, Clayton; Lewis, Colleen; Margolis, Jane; McCartney, Robert; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Nowack, Palle.; Orton, Kai.; Perez, Lance; Pontelli, Enrico; Repenning, Alex; Resnick, Mitchel; Roberts, Eric; Rodger, Susan; Sahami, Mehran; Simon, Beth; Soh, Leen-Kiat; Sorby, Sheryl; Stefik, Andreas; Strobel, Johannes; Tashakkori, Rahman.; Tenenberg, Josh; Wieman, Carl; Wilensky, Uri; Yadav, Aman; Computer science--Study and teaching
Collection Contents
- White papers, 2013; 43 computer file(s) (PDF)
  - Broadening Participation in Computing
    - Ashcraft, Catherine, University of Colorado - Boulder, Increasing the Participation of Women and Underrepresented Minorities in Computing: Missing Perspectives and New Directions, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Brown, Quincy, Bowie State, MOTIVATE: An Opportunity to Impact African American High School Girls, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Denner, Jill, ETR Associates, Community College Students and Computer Science: A Call for Research on Enrollment and Persistence among Underrepresented Groups, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - DiSalvo, Betsy, Georgia Tech, Navigating Motivations to Not Learn Computer Science, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Guzdial, Mark, Georgia Tech, Making Programming Meaningful to Induce Passion for Broadening Computing, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Hodari, Apriel, Council for Opportunity in Education, Struggle, Strive and Surprise: How Womanist Perspectives Might Broaden Participation in Computer Science, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Ladner, Richard, University of Washington, Including Students with Disabilities in Computing Education for the 21st Century, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Lewis, Clayton, University of Colorado - Boulder, Nonvisual Access to Computation and Programming, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Margolis, Jane, UCLA, That Classroom “Magic:” What are the characteristics of an effective pre-college teaching practice for broadening participation in computing …….and how do we know?, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Pontelli, Enrico, New Mexico State, Exploring Non-Scientific Disciplines as a K-12 Vehicle to Carry Computational Thinking: An Agenda, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Stefik, Andreas, UNLV, The Elephant in the Room, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
  - K-12
    - Boyer, Kristy, North Carolina State, Toward a Computer Science Learning Progression: Investigating the Role of Adaptive Learning Environments for K–12, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Brennan, Karen, Harvard University, Social Dimensions of Computing Education, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Caspersen, Michael, and Nowack, Palle, Aarhus University - Denmark, Model Based Thinking & Practice, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Fisler, Kathi, WPI, Two Themes: Language Bias and Informal Education on Secure Coding, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Gardner-McCune, Christina, Clemson University, A Case for Learning Research in Computer Science Education, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Goode, Joanna, University of Oregon, That Classroom “Magic:” What are the characteristics of an effective pre-college teaching practice for broadening participation in computing …….and how do we know?, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Grover, Shuchi, Stanford University, Research Imperatives for CS Education in K-12, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Kolikant, Yifat Ben-David, Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Professional lives amidst instability with the help of a crowd, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Resnick, Mitchel, MIT, How can we help a more diverse range of young people become fluent with computational technologies?, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Yadav, Aman, Purdue University, Professional Development for CS Teachers: A Framework and its Implementation, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
  - STEM Education
    - Dann, Wanda, Carnegie Mellon University, Parallelism and Concurrency, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Lewis, Colleen, Harvey Mudd College, Understanding the Connection between CS and Other Domains, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Orton, Kai, Northwestern University, Embedding Computational Thinking in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (CT-STEM), 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Perez, Lance, University of Nebraska, Abstract Thinking and Problem Solving in Undergraduate STEM Curricula, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Repenning, Alex, University of Colorado - Boulder, Scalable Game Design: Broadening Participation by Integrating Game Design and Science Simulation Building into Middle School Curricula, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Sorby, Sheryl, Ohio State University, The Case for Spatial Skills Instruction in Computer Science, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Strobel, Johannes, Texas A&M, CS Education and Engineering Education: Joint Research to Develop Students' Interest and Success, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Wilensky, Uri, Northwestern University, Computational Thinking Through Modeling and Simulation, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
  - Structure/Policy
    - Century, Jeanne, University of Chicago, Developing Research-Informed Instructional Resources to Support Broad Scale Access to High Quality Computer Science Education: A Research Agenda, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Doane, William, IDA-STPI, Computing Education Research, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Roberts, Eric, Stanford University, Computer Science Education Research Priorities for the Next Five Years, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
  - Students and Learning
    - Bienkowski, Marie, SRI, Building Evidence and Building Practice in Computer Science Education, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Danielak, Brian, University of Wisconsin, Students as designers of programs: Why we should and how we can study the practices and artifacts that lead to students' final code, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Edwards, Stephen, Virginia Tech, Continuous Data-driven Learning Assessment, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Eisenberg, Michael, University of Colorado - Boulder, Computer Science Education as an Aspect of the Maker Movement, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Fenwick, James B., Kurtz, Barry L., and Tashakkori, Rahman, Appalachian State University, Using the Learning Cycle in Computer Science Education, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Fincher, Sally, University of Kent, The Quantified Learner, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Hundhausen, Christopher, Washington State University, Leveraging Analyses of Big Data on Computing Students’ Programming and Social Interaction Processes to Build More Effective Programming Environments and Pedagogical Interventions, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Kafai, Yasmin, University of Pennsylvania, Rebooting Competitions: Reviewing, Recalibrating and Reimagining Public Events for Supporting Computing, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Lee, Cynthia, Stanford University, Adapting to Pervasive Computing, and Making Great Pedagogy, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - McCartney, Robert, University of Connecticut, How do computer scientists develop during their university studies?, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Rodger, Susan, Duke University, Visualization and Interaction in Learning Computer Science Concepts, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Sahami, Mehran, Stanford University, Expanding Computer Science Education by Developing Scalable Methods for Assessment, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Soh, Leen-Kiat, University of Nebraska, Investigating and Understanding the Role and Impact of Creative Thinking and Competency on Improving CS Education, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
    - Tenenberg, Josh, University of Washington - Tacoma, Reframing research questions in CS education: unpacking the suppositions about mind and activity, 2013; 1 computer file(s) (PDF)